everybody wanted the atat from the Star
Wars wow it's a really exciting toy
or is it yeah his legs moving that and
the 80s ones had guns that moved and lit
up but you have to put your hand in to
operate its head and yeah the legs move
if you operate them with your hands
wouldn't it be better if it walked along
now I'm aware of a walking at a tea toy
which was made by thinkway but this was
quite a bit smaller and didn't really
walk amazingly well mostly its feet are
just sliding on the ground I suspect it
had a similar mechanism to the 3D
printed ones that have been going around
and ultimately that's because licensed
toys cost a lot to produce so cutting
down on Motors and control Electronics
is generally how things go in the toy
industry otherwise the product ends up
costing too much I've built quite a few
four-legged walking robots in the past I
spent years through multiple versions of
robot dogs before I got to something
that could move fast and was Dynamic but
I actually started with bipedal robots
like my the Star Wars gonk droid which
walked Along on two legs at the time I
thought if I can make something not too
bad that walks on two legs and four legs
should be easy but what I didn't
consider was that the gong drop had big
flat feet and typically robot dogs have
much smaller pointy feet which is why it
took me so very many versions to make a
robot dog that walked well but I never
went back to build a four-legged walking
robot with big flat feet to see how easy
that would be and the at 80 is a great
robot to convert because it's got these
great big flat feet with these
stabilizing toes I'm going to use a very
similar parallelogram leg mechanism to
the gong Droid which had a gear
reduction built into the leg I worked
out the geometry for this in the gong
Droid series which you can check out in
my channel essentially though it's a
motor with a Spur Gear Running on a
large partial gear and as I demonstrated
in the previous videos the large gear
just needs to be the same radius as the
top part of the parallelogram and then
the gears track each other just fine
instead of a DC motor this time I'm
going to use some servos with a gear
mounted on the servo horn just a quick
ad for my 3D printing sponsor thanks to
lol's bar for supporting my Channel with
3D printers having lots of printers
really helps get the projects done in
time obviously we have to make four of
everything because it has four legs and
in some cases that's actually more parts
the legs themselves have four sections
so we have to make 16 sticks to make our
four parallelogram legs and here's one
of the gears that goes on the servo
right all my parts are printed so we're
ready to do some assembly thanks to 3D
fuel for the filament for this this is
all pro pla plus so here are my gears
for the servo there's a recess so that
that gear can get really close to the
servo body but obviously those little
things sticking up are probably going to
snap off it'll be okay though because
the bulk of the gear is just fine the
servo itself fits into a Servo bracket
which is 3D printed and yes I remember
to leave the hole for the cable to come
out just on the end there so we can
screw them in
that bracket fits onto one of the pieces
of the leg there and obviously there's a
recess so that the gear can turn without
binding on it
the other side of the leg has that
partial spur gear on and that binds
nicely onto the gear that we've got so
now we just need to install something on
each end so that we've got our
parallelogram I've got some three
millimeter steel axles so now we can put
together the parallelogram and now we've
got a working mechanism with a motor in
it so giving that Servo a signal on some
power we can see that moves quite nicely
and that Servo tracks the big gear
perfectly just because the big gear is
the same radius as the top part of the
parallelogram so that's worked out well
again really happy if how that's turned
out there's hardly any slop in this as
well so it's actually quite a rigid
mechanism so with these stages stacked
together there's going to be hardly any
wobble in the legs so all we need to do
now is build the top of the leg and then
build four more of them and put it all
together so here's one whole leg with
its two stages so it can bend in the
middle so that gives us quite a wide
range of motion we've got a big enough
stripe there to walk like an AT-AT and
of course we can bend the leg as well to
pick it up so if we Bend both Motors in
the same direction then we can pick the
leg up and that gives us enough ground
clearance to take steps
but before we put the rest of the parts
for that together it's time for a quick
ad from the video sponsor which is
curiositystream curiosity stream offers
many award-winning documentary series
that you can't find anywhere else the
content spans many factual topics
including science technology engineering
nature history food and lots lots more
so there's something for everyone
curiosity stream plan starts at just
five dollars a month you can choose a
monthly or annual plan and get access to
thousands of hours of quality content
and is available on multiple devices
like your TV computer and also mobile
devices so you can watch your favorite
content on the go all content on
curiosity stream is factual so there's a
big focus on education whether it's
science technology or history the
documentaries are informative and
engaging obviously I really like science
and technology so I really like the
series called Engineering in the future
which covers the metaverse hyperloop
technology space exploration flying cars
but also includes a documentary about
Timber skyscrapers go to
curiositystream.com jamesbrussin or scan
the QR code for unlimited access to the
world's top documentaries and
non-fiction series and for my fans use
promo code James Bruton and you'll get
25 off so click the link below or go to
curiositystream.com jamesbroughton and
save 25 right now
right time to get back to the attacks
so I made the whole thing four times so
we've got four legs each one has two
servos so that's eight servos but then
there's another four servos at the top
and that's going to enable the robot to
turn so we've got a plate that goes on
the bottom and the top and I've just got
some bolts which are put through there
so we've got pivot Points and then we've
got a Servo for each leg that runs on a
larger gear on the top plate so that we
can swing the legs outwards I thought it
was a shame to tear the head and body
off the original at A T so I'm printing
a new one and this is printed on the
lolsbot Tas long bed which has a really
long bed for big parts
so my proportions aren't quite the same
as the original toy but I'm pretty happy
with the way it's turned out and I think
mechanically it's going to be pretty
solid the headphones printing right now
but we're going to put some Electronics
in so as usual I've got an Arduino Mega
that's more than enough to control those
servos and it's got this piece of strip
board with all these wires broken out of
it with power and the signal
distribution for the 12 servos it's got
an RC receiver on it the orange thing on
there that's because we're going to be
using my universal remote I made which
is a DSM remote so check that out and my
channel right let's uh try and get all
this wired up so we've got all those
Electronics installed and the cables
rooted as best possible and zip tied on
and we've also got the head installed
the Arduino lives in there and the main
battery lives right at the back so I've
just tied the controller to the servos
for now so they all Bend in the same
direction and you can see the whole
thing goes up and down as it bends its
legs as you'd expect and also quite
helpfully it can stand on one leg so
those stabilizing feet really help to
keep it upright you wouldn't be able to
do that with one of my open dog projects
but it would just fall over in that
direction
but in order to take steps with one foot
at a time what we actually need is it
goes forwards is all of the other feet
to slide back in a perfectly straight
line now this is actually quite a
complicated mechanism here to do that
and we're going to do it properly so
we're going to calculate some inverse
kinematics I did a more in-depth video
about this before where I builds a
simple robot arm the calculations I did
for this allow me to position the end of
the arm into Cartesian coordinates that
means up and down and left and right in
straight lines the code running
calculates the required joint angles for
the two joints I use Pythagoras Theorem
and trigonometry to work out the angles
the at 80 is very similar if we consider
the leg to be a triangle so first I
worked out the angles from the required
length of the leg which is easy because
we know all three sides once this is
done we can set the leg length and the
code will work out the angles next we
need to move the foot back and forth we
can just imagine that the leg is a
straight line since we can set its
length already so we can imagine another
right angle triangle where we give it
the distance we want to move back and
forth the height of the body and then
use trigonometry to work out the
shoulder angle and the new leg length we
pass the new leg length onto the
previous calculation and then the body
will stay at the same height as the foot
moves back and forth the only thing I
didn't take into account properly was
this piece of the leg here because these
two joints don't meet so it's not a
perfect triangle but I just ignored that
and it works perfectly well so now we
can actually move that body up and down
as we did before but instead of just
moving those servos directly coupled to
the stick we're actually calculating
trigonometry and working out the leg
length and now I can pretty much slide
backwards and forwards as well in a
straight line so if you look at the
cabinet behind me you'll find that body
is tracking it at some point those
servos do reach their end stops though
and also the cheap hobby servos have
quite low tolerance feedback pots in
probably about 10 tolerance so that
means you probably don't get a linear
response out of them that along with the
broken triangle at the knee means that
we don't get a perfectly straight line
in any direction but we've got enough
that we can make it walk and the legs
move backwards and forwards in pretty
much a straight line so we can take
steps
so obviously I can move the feet
independently and we can put a step
sequencer together to make it take steps
you can see the foot doesn't track the
ground perfectly but it's good enough
for our purposes
there's one other issue we need to solve
though if I move my hand along the table
here so it tracks in a perfectly
straight line You'll see that my arm
gets longer in this position and it gets
longer in this position as we move
further away from the center but you'll
also notice that my shoulder is moving a
lot more than my elbow the elbow joint
hardly ever moves and my shoulder makes
most of the motion so if we were just to
send the two servos of the leg to
another position in a straight line like
this then one has to move further than
the other and if we just send them at
the speed that the servos will go at
which is their maximum speed then
basically one is going to get there
first the other one will catch up later
and that means we won't be moving in a
perfectly straight line anymore when I'm
driving the joints manually effectively
I'm scrolling through all the positions
from A to B because I'm moving this
thick quite slowly through all the
positions over time and the math is
being calculated 100 times a second to
work out the joint angles and therefore
the leg tracks in a straight line from
point A to point B but if I was just to
suddenly send a step from one position
to the next then those two joints will
move them maximum speed and one will get
there faster than the other so what we
need is something that will manually
scroll through all the positions but do
it automatically when we specify two
points and to do that we can use the
Arduino ramp Library the simplest demo
for that is specifying two points and
then opening a Serial plotter and seeing
the interpolation between them which is
a nice straight line instead of a square
wave or a step that new interpolated
value is fed into the inverse kinematics
so all the way through that value
changing over time recalculates the
joint angles and our feet move in a
straight line from position to position
I'm also using motion filtering on my
control sticks and on the servos
themselves on the output so I made a
video specifically about this you should
check out where I made a robot head with
really cheap servos and controlled it
with an 8-bit Arduino and you can see
the Motions are really smooth there as I
move around and basically all I'm doing
is taking a large percentage of the
previous value in the loop and only a
small percentage of the new ones so the
values can't change too quick and we get
this lovely deceleration on the moves
so now if I switch a switch on the
controller we've got a timed sequence
running that lifts each foot in turn
pretty much the way a dog walks if I
push forward on one of my control sticks
then it takes the multiple of that
control stick and moves all of the feet
backwards which are on the ground and
the one forward which is off the ground
and so it walks along pretty
convincingly and pretty much how an
AT-AT walks flicking another switch
causes it to lift diagonal legs and if I
turn one of the controllers that causes
the legs to swing out at the appropriate
time to make it turn the legs don't
share a common pivot point and that
pivot point isn't in the middle of the
robot which means the feet should
actually move position in and out as it
rotates round but I didn't care about
that and it's light enough it doesn't
matter so it walks okay it's very wobbly
side to side you'll notice though
although that only happens when it walks
forwards if I reverse things and walk
backwards which I can do just by pulling
the stick in the other direction then
it's actually much more stable you'll
notice his bottom is much more stable
than the head was when it was walking
the other way and that is because the
head is making it front heavy already
but when it pushes all its legs back
apart from the one that's in the air
that makes it even more front heavy I
tried to add Mass to the back by putting
a battery on the back outside the back
and also having some nuts there to add
some extra mass it's pretty hard to
compensate for the 300 grams hanging so
far out the front though
[Music]
foreign
that means at iet's will work if the
Star Wars was real life you'd actually
be able to send one into battle and it
will walk along it's quite good to know
that they're statically stable so it can
take one leg off the ground and still
stand there with it off the ground it
doesn't need to put it down again to
catch itself because we all know what
happens when at 18s fall over I'm going
to publish all the cannon go for this
project so if you want to have a look at
it or build your own you can and that's
on GitHub it's totally open source so if
you want to support me through patreon
or YouTube channel membership then those
links are in the description below and
patrons and YouTube channel members can
get access to all the videos up to a
week early sneak peeks and pictures of
what's coming up and Discord benefits